welcome to meditative legendre Vicki I'm
a cognitive psychologist and cognitive
scientist at the University of Toronto
there I study scientifically
academically mindfulness related
phenomena like Insight flow mystical
experience transformative experience the
cultivation of wisdom I've also been a
practitioner of a past meditation medic
contemplation in Tai Chi Chuan and
Chacon for over 29 years I've been
teaching it professionally for close to
20 years this is a progressive course if
you're joining us for the first time
you're welcome to to stay but you've
missed four teaching lessons you can go
back into the playlist on my channel and
you can find the number of lessons
lessons one through those see the
exercises in order to teach an important
principle you practice and that's how
you can catch up with us normally what
we do is Monday is Dharma day that's a
game which I do with teaching I'll do
that today and then for the remainder of
the weekdays Tuesday through Friday we
still meet at my thirty but what I do is
do review and we sit together at the end
of every session including Monday's
there your name so a reminder of that
schedule change we only do teaching days
now on Mondays Dharma days and that
there are no classes on the weekend
Saturdays and Sundays all right so today
is going to be a longer lesson than
normal for a teacher because I have sort
of a lot that needs to be taught
together I don't want to break it up and
that is today I'm going to teach you a
contemplative practice that complements
a meditative practice now there's a lot
of sort of confusion to run a lot of the
terms that I'm going to be using today
in teaching and so that's why I have to
go carefully and unpack them and try to
present particular interpretations of
these terms one is for example the start
these two terms get to tend to be used
interchangeably meditation contemplation
I believe that's a mistake and you could
notice that as I've shown you the word
meditation refers to this practice of
moving in we've talked about you know
finding your Center moving towards the
center that kind of thing and
contemplation the word contemplate here
that has at the root temple are the
Latin for to look out to look up to the
sky it's also a translation of the Greek
word theoria was where we get a word
theory from Authority orient needs to
look deeply into reality see so do you
see the difference meditation is about
this looking deeply in word and
contemplation is about looking deeply at
work and you need the two together
think about our metaphor of standing
back and looking at the glasses in
meditation
okay so we stick this is meditation
standing back looking at right that's
good looking at the mind rather than
automatically through it I hope you're
getting to see I'm useful and important
that it's but suppose you think you sees
Distortion
how do you know if you know no longer
your glasses are no longer distorting
your vision we have to put them on you
have to put them on and look out and see
if you can now see they're friendly you
see um you complement meditation with
contemplation you're not actually
engaging in a process of transformation
you need to be doing the two together
this is of course one of the things that
my work on insight is you need right
when I didn't say you you have to step
back from the inappropriate framing
you're in but you often look through
right to a new and more encompassing
framing my meister eckhart spirits work
for this that has been sort of actually
reduced it meaning to just meaning an
insight is dirt brooke breakthrough you
have to break the old frame but you have
to move through to the new frame so
meditation and contemplation are not
ethical they compliment and correct and
need each other
and I was privileged as a as I said to
be taught of these three together
meditative practice for pasta a
contemplative practice Metta and a
moving flowing practice touch each one
because all three of those are really
conducive to what we're going to talk
about much later in the course
Praja wisdom okay so meta okay so now we
face another issue because meta is
become quite popular in North America
and I want to challenge the popular
notion of meta that people might be
familiar with because I think it's not
the most felicitous interpretation of
the meta practice I don't think it goes
well I don't think it sits well with the
Buddhist sutras and I don't think it
sits well with our best cognitive
science so I want to I want to compare
that's why I need this time so I'm
really asking for your patience this
morning I want to compare the emotional
interpretation of meta and ET ta a
contemplative practice with the
existential interpretation though so the
emotional interpretation is that meta is
largely about generating positive
feelings towards all beers and this is
problematic yet in a lot of ways first
of all it confuses feelings and emotions
and that it confuses emotions with what
meta is take a look at the word in
English that is most frequently used to
translate meta which is loving-kindness
notice it's a hybrid word it's a hybrid
word first of all it's made up of loving
and first thing we should notice that
love itself is not an emotion this is a
mistake people get into which means it's
even less appealing I mean if I'm if I
love someone their presence will make me
happy their absence you make me sad
they're being under threat can make me
angry love is not an emotion even less a
feeling love is a way of being it's a
way of knowing and it's a way of being
known it's a it's a commitment
- a way of life with someone so love in
itself is something much more
existential than emotional what about
kindness
well kindness isn't itself an emotion
it's not even a feeling kindness is a
virtue being to be kind is a way of
being virtuous the original meaning of
the word kindness when you go back in
Old English is what's called the why by
the way I had to do with initially
causing an increase and then later with
noble deeds you see it was it was the
act of sort of opening things up in a
virtuous manner now think of the word
virtue the word virtue like virtual
virtue is having a power having a
capacity so what if I have the virtue of
courage I have the capacity to see
through the illusions of fear into what
needs to be done if I have the combined
the virtue of temperance I have the
capacity to see through the illusions of
greed and do what needs to be done so
I've got this existential attitude love
which is a positive existential attitude
for sure and it affords a virtue it
gives me the power to see through a kind
of a lesion into what needs to be done
see the word loving-kindness is this
hybrid word because it's specifically
not an emotional term it's an inter
categorical term it's trying to put
together things that that for which we
don't have a singular English term it's
putting together
there's existential stance of love love
and active and kindness which is virtue
okay
so let's say that like what's happening
are there positive emotions being
invoked in Metta yes I'll explain those
to you but what I want you to understand
is that the positive emotions are not
the goal that's the that's I think the
primary mistake of the emotional
interpretation of Metta the positive
emotions are a method by which we get an
existential stance that allows us to see
through an important kind of a lesion
and into what needs to be done
so what is an existential mode then if
the emotional interpretation of meta is
inadequate it's too simplistic it's to
truncate it
what is this deeper meaning well
thankfully we have two really important
sources both of them who were deeply
familiar with the Buddhist tradition we
have erich fromm and he was also deeply
familiar with historic tradition because
this what I'm going to talk about was
also discovered basically I think in
this dark tradition and we have Stephen
Baxter in his book on Buddhism an
existential interpretation of Buddhism
called alone with others okay let's what
is an existential mode so what I want
you to think about is a process that is
all happening all the time but it's
normally happening automatically
unconsciously and reactively what's that
process it's a process that I call pel
identification what does that mean it
means that whenever I go into any
situation I'm automatically assuming a
particular identity right now I'm a
teacher and I'm automatically assigning
identities you're my students this wall
isn't just the wall it's it's my support
right because I'm assuming the identity
of a meditator when I'm not assuming the
identity of a meditator this isn't to
support it's just a wall it's just a
barrier so I'm always assuming an
identity and an assigning an identity
and we're doing this both with other
people and as I just indicated with the
wall with objects so the existential
mode is how that process of Co
identification is is occurring in you
now the thing about this and this is was
Erich Fromm's deep insight but Steven
Batchelor came to it independently many
people have actually converged on this
across different wisdom traditions both
Western and Eastern is that there's two
really important existential modes we
have to talk about they're oriented
around some of our fundamental needs
let's talk about one that from calls the
having mode the having mode is your
existential mode the kind of identities
you assume and assign and those are Co
determining when you're trying to meet
your having needs these are needs that
are
by having something I need to have water
I need to have food there is nothing
immoral or wrong about this by the way I
don't have water and I don't have food
if I prefer if I pursue that kind of
self-denial which was rejected
ultimately by the Buddha then I will die
so notice what I have to do that control
of things I have to bring them under my
control I have to be able to consume
them oxygen water air shelter we consume
shelter away and we're aware of all of
this very acutely right now all right
this is very important and notice
something about these needs right
they require me to solve problems very
readily and in order to do that the kind
of identities I assigned to things are
categorical identities this is the
identity something has by belonging to a
category because when it belongs to a
category I can predict its behavior I
can familiarize myself with it I can
control and manipulate it to solve my
problems this is a pen I readily and
quickly recognize it as a pen it's like
it reminds me of many other pans I've
had in the past
if I lose this pen I readily know what
to look for in order to replace it and
that's good because I need to be able to
use my pens readily effectively okay so
this is the follow Martin Buber this is
what's called an eye it relationship
there's nothing wrong with ayet
relationships because you need to have
categorical identifications with things
right and in order to do that in order
to satisfy your having needs what kind
of eye is it that's related to it well
it's a manipulator it's somebody that's
a problem solver a categorise er a
controller and a consumer again that's
not evil okay that is necessary for your
homeostatic needs but it's not their
only existential mode you have another
existential mode these this is what Prom
calls the being mode I think the
becoming mode is a little bit more
accurate but it's his term
so we'll use it that way these like this
existential mode the kind of identity
you assume at the kind of identities you
assign this existential mode is built
around your developmental needs your
needs of BA these are needs that are not
met by controlling and consuming things
these are needs that are met by but
coming right coming into being so I need
to become mature I need to be mature
right I need to be in love right then
it's that's a state of becoming it's a
kind of person of becoming I need to be
courageous I need to become kinder these
needs are met by going through
transformation and so your relationship
to your identity is fundamentally
different and the identities you are
assigned to things if that's even the
right word now are not categorical
identities there are the identities by
which you come to transformation not
controlling consumption the
transformation think of the prototypical
relationship of identification or
development when you are in a loving
relationship with someone when you when
you come into a relationship with your
beloved you don't relate to them I it
you don't relate to them categorically
if I was to say to my beloved partner
that I'm with her because she readily
reminds me of all other women so that I
can easily predict and control her
behavior I'm in trouble in that
relationship I have really radically
miss framed it and she is going to
reject because she doesn't want to be
very rightly so on it that I control her
manipulate she wants to be a dhow with
whom I'm in a relationship of mutual
development and becoming we are
reciprocally opening each other up
better you
by the way you open up and go through
transformation and what you're in
relationship or who you're in
relationship is also opening up and
going through transformation and that
mutual reciprocal opening that mutual
transformation that's what the research
shows when people do that with each
other they fall into love romantic love
friendship love etc okay so this
existential mode of like the B mode is
not about controlling and
problem-solving it's about coming into a
relationship where we're reciprocally
opening with things I though because we
are identifying with them in a way of
mutual transformation each one of us is
bound to realizing the more Ness of the
other how they and that's there so
people when we're in a loving
relationship we're not finished with
them we don't consume them we don't ever
know them completely there's always a
mystery to the person this of course
happens when we take objects and we
change them from being categorical to
being those when we make an object into
a work of art we're supposed to come in
to listen to my word a contemplative
relationship with it so that the work of
art more and more discloses itself to us
and we and more and more disclose
ourselves to it we fall in love with it
and we become other than what we are and
it becomes other than what it initially
was that resonating more ness in the
mystery between the mystery within you
and the mystery without and why is this
all important well because people fall
into modal confusion they use the wrong
mode for the needs that they're trying
to meet and you can see things like
stoicism in the West and Buddhism in the
East as trying to get us to realize this
is what ramen I should argue this modal
confusion what would modal confusion
look like I need to become mature so I
have a car
see what I'm doing I'm trying to meet my
being needs from the wrong existential
mode I'm trying to meet my being needs
from the having mode and so I'm
frustrated I'm not actually becoming
mature so I need a better car maybe more
cars I need to be in love so I'm gonna
have lots of sex I need to be courageous
I'm going to have power right again it's
not the having mood is wrong the error
the Deeb error the existential error is
modal confusion little confusion what
Mehta is designed to do arguing is to
first awaken us to the process of code
identification that's normally happening
unconsciously automatically reactively
and then awaken us prom modal confusion
so that whatever we're relating to we
have the capacity when it is appropriate
to do so virtue us to know it by loving
it which doesn't mean feeling affection
or having emotions are feeling it means
being in the being mode with
relationship to it that's why I even
hesitate to use the word love because we
have so reduced love to an emotion and
then so reduced emotions to feelings
I think it's an even a mistake to use
that word now so instead this is what
I'm trying to teach you this notion of
coming awake to existential modes
process the process of Co identification
and then awaking from how we can be
mortally confused because this is the
key sati means to deeply remember but
not remember the level of facts it means
to remember the being mode to remember
to recover to be able to live within the
being mode so that your being needs
ultimately better so the positive
emotions that we invoke in Metta are
the goal the posit so what Fredrickson's
worked on positive emotion shows is that
what positive emotions do is they they
broadened and built they open us up they
open us up to transformation and
learning they open us up to that
reciprocal opening they are an
affordance they make passable the
remembering of the existential modes and
then the remembering especially of the
being mode of seeing through the
illusion of Moodle confusion so this is
why and I think this makes great sense
and I've pointed out some names people
and there are others this is this is I
think the correct interpretation of meta
in the Buddhist sutras and it lines up
with similar practices and very
convergent across multiple wisdom
traditions so that's why I'm critical of
the emotional interpretation that is so
common and pervasive we want to be able
to take the Posada insight not in our
mind but to the level of our being we
want to take it into our existential
mode that's the kind of insight we
walked okay so we've talked about how we
need a contemplative practice to
compliment a meditative practice I
talked to you about what the
contemplative practices are going to
teach you meta and I've given you the
existential interpretation of the meta
practice how do we actually do it how do
we actually do it well this is how we
actually do it we take time to do to get
into the passive we always we Center we
root we find our flow we find our focus
then we're going to move to a mantra and
the mantra is now again not something
the mana is like the lenses you're
looking through and the mantra is right
wherever you're whoever you're directing
meta to to you get the traditional form
is may X be happy and healthy or may I
realize X
X is true suchness or a more modern one
or more recent one that I would propose
to you is may I see the more nests in X
which doesn't necessarily mean you like
them or have affection or positive
feelings for them but you're trying to
change your relationship from a having
mode to your being mowed you're trying
to first of all become aware so we start
with meta towards ourselves so maybe
it's me I realize the more nests of John
what happens when you try to connect to
and identify with yourself when you
direct a sense of connectedness to
yourself what does that feel like in
your mind your body do you tense up are
you sort of thrilled is it kind of not
just for you does it feel empty so first
of all always what's the embodied taste
of it and then try to sense first of all
get into that embodied sense always the
embodied sense and then within that
don't try to make but try to see are you
having it yourself or are you becoming
yourself is yourself a thing that is
within you that you hold onto your
identity oh you're the same or is
yourself actually an ongoing unfolding
process that's always in relation to the
world can you shift from having yourself
to being yourself but that doesn't mean
just expressing your true self where
that means realize yourself as a process
in development that there's more to you
than what you know it's the kind of
humility
so first become a weight really deeply
sense as you direct meta toward yourself
may I be happy and healthy maybe use the
traditional may I realized my suchness
may I realize what more is here try the
experiment with what you're trying to do
is to come into a sense of what kind of
identity are you assumed
and assigning to yourself maybe it's
your role on the teacher you identified
with your persona
maybe it's your personality I'm a
happy-go-lucky person these are things
you have what kind of identification are
you doing and is it ultimately having or
beer now next you do Metta towards
somebody you're close to somebody maybe
I'll pick my son Jason right and I call
it the image of Jason in my mind and I
direct method towards that may Jason be
happy and healthy or may I realize
Jason's suchness or a meat may I see
more in Jason and what I'm trying to do
is again first of all what identity do I
assume I'm his father
he is my son I'm assuming that I said
identity but of course he's much more
than that
and I can be much more to him I have to
unlock my identity to realize more of
his identity I have to get it into
reciprocal opening so what identity am i
assuming what does that feel like in my
mind in my body when I assume that
identity what identity am i assigning
and am I having him because we often try
to live vicariously through our kids
even if we have wonderful affection for
them we could be having them or are we
in the being mode can we first so I want
to wake up to the pillow identification
and I want to potentially wake up start
to see through any modal confusion there
might be there now I picked a neutral
person maybe somebody at your
convenience or somebody who delivers
things for you like somebody you just
know generically it's direct meta
towards them maybe the traditional
you don't know their name just their
image may you be happy and healthy or
may I realize you're such Nisour I'm a I
realized what's more about you what
identity do you assume towards a generic
person what identity do you assigned do
you just help them are they just a unit
and you remember the being mode with
respect to them the next
is the person that you're in conflict
with potentially the tradition calls it
your enemy you may not have any enemies
people dedicated to your destruction we
may have people you're in conflict with
even people that you love
call out the image and the name of the
person that you're in conflict with
direct meta towards them what identity
are you assigning what identity are you
assuming I'm the victim
they're the villain I'm the Conqueror
they're the defeated what identities are
you assuming what identities are you're
assigning and are you alternately having
yourself and having them are you locked
in the having mode can you remember
Satya the being mode which doesn't mean
necessarily having affection feelings or
forgiving them it means remembering the
being mode not getting locked into the
having mode and then finally we direct
meta towards all be all human beings
some people directed towards all
sentient beings I recommend all human
beings and you don't worry about getting
accurate image you're probably just
imagine a crowd of people that's fine
direct meta what identity do you assume
what identity did you assign as a human
person and is that something you have or
can you remember the being mode okay so
let's review you go in to the pasta
always always always find your Center
find your route find your flow find your
focus do a bit of a pasta then pick up
meta the contemplative practice direct
meta toward yourself your heart area may
I be happy and healthy or may I realize
my suchness the suchness is wet what
your what what it what is that about you
that goes beyond your categorical
identities or may I see more
may I see more where it may I realize
the mortis right and again first awaken
to the co identification what identities
are coming into mind and into body
what identities are you assigning and
assuming if the feel that deep feel the
deep
of that identification process and then
see if right how much of it is a habit
can you catch a sense of what it is to
shift into the being mode in
relationship to yourself and then to
somebody you're close with probably
three or four times for each one don't
do the mantra quickly do it slowly
mindfully that's why you set up the
pasta first somebody you're close with
somebody you're neutral with somebody
you're in conflict with and then all
people okay so this will be different
for T and that because you're doing a
contemplative practice and it's very
mantra based however one thing is the
same if you're distracted label the
distraction with an ING word return to
your breath the friending yourself and
notice how all of meta is about learning
how to the friend because friendship is
ultimately a way of being a way of
reciprocally opening it's a virtue okay
so you come back you label the
distraction with an ING word you come
back to your breath do a few breaths of
the pasta then return to where you were
in meta and do that whole I say yeah I
was in the neutral person start from the
beginning of the neutral person and do
your four recitations of the Metra when
you go back okay all right now
unfortunately we have to set a timer
I recommend normally don't set a timer
with meta pick a number of recitations
you're going to do for each area for
five or six and then do them slowly and
mindfully and then when you're done
you're done
unfortunately going to need to set a
timer for today we'll set the timer
because we're already over we'll set it
for 12 minutes all right so do your the
pasta sort of as quickly as you possibly
can I don't want to rush you but but I
want so you get some time and you get a
sense of what it is to do better
all right we'll begin when I say
baguette all right begin
you
slowly began to come out of your
practice not just you cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition you're not
trying to just they take your life
you're trying to educate yourself for
your life Matta is particularly powerful
to try and bring into your everyday
consciousness and cognition because it
is trying to will reawaken to be in mode
and you can have the being mode towards
things in your environment as you look
around try to get into what would it be
to remember the being load of things it
brings with it a sense of wonder a
glimmer and sometimes of all also it
reveals things that might be unpleasant
that you're avoiding seeing in things
because you're letting things come into
their item of their mortis and identity
beyond the identity that you're trying
to hold on for them one more time that
remind you the having mode is not evil
you're not trying to avoid the having
mode you're trying to not fall prey to
modal confusion so the pasta and meta
are like to two feet by which you walk
the path the pasta and meta the pasta
and meta meta meditation contemplation
meditation contemplation created insight
remembering the being mode affording
insight remembering the being mode until
we get deep inside deep transformative
insight so we get a profound remembering
of the being mode that's what we're
after after and that is most conducive
to you right satisfying those needs for
meaning that are only found within the
being mode we'll talk later about how we
don't want to confuse like the event
with the meaning of events right now
let's break free as much as we can dirt
break through the mode of confusion a
right I won't have time for too many
questions right now cuz we're already
significantly over our time I will
answer a lot of questions it would be
good if everybody tried met up a couple
of times I recommend that you try to do
the past not alternate if you're only
going to practice once a day which is
fine do the past on one day better than
next if you're doing or want to do two
things per day this is a way of doing if
it's a little easier they're trying to
do just for pasta twice you can do met
up perhaps in the morning sorry you can
do the pasta perhaps in the morning and
met if the evening or vice versa play
around with it until you find what works
but try to now alternate between the two
of them did you want to start to get the
two feeds going the to the two feet
going so it's really important to always
keep both of these and always remember
don't go directly into meta get the
pasta going find your core for and find
the pasta first I don't know if there's
any questions I what I'm going to
recommend is we're already over time for
today considerably 10 minutes or so so
I'm going to recommend that what we do
is that we we're going to we're going to
table literally all these questions and
I'll make sure they get addressed I'll
try and increase and because tomorrow
we'll just review the Q&A maybe for 15
minutes and get a lot of question and
answers about meta for you tomorrow I
want to thank you all for joining and
really encourage you to practice medic
not just not just for pasta
I want to thank as always tomorrow my
techno mage and Jason my beloved son
please subscribe to this channel so that
you could get notifications so that it's
easier for you to find the playlist go
back to the other teaching lessons you
can also find a whole host of videos by
lectures in awakening for the meeting
crisis on this whole idea of sati
awakening to go identification and
awakening from wild confusion
t at the existential remembering of the
being mode huh please think about
inviting others who might benefit by
sharing this series I'm offering this
because I think it is beneficial many of
you are saying it's helpful and it would
be very good if we could extend this as
widely as possible to help as many
people as possible we'll be doing this
every weekday morning at 9:30 est from
there for the rest of the week I will be
review it I'll go over met again I'll
answer questions throughout the whole of
the week that way we would take the
whole week to really sink our teeth very
deeply into this practice thank you very
much everyone for your time and
attention
keep up your practice they will
transform you and your life